i was reflecting
today on
what is the common thread
what is in common to all everything
that's unwholesome what is
what is the common thread between
everything that's unwholesome
and wholesome acts
so i've got my own thoughts on that but
what do you think must tell me what you
reflected
to me it's anything
when you attempt to take away that which
is
would conceal that which is with that
which isn't so certain
so certain
contradiction then there's a certain
discrepancy yeah that's what's in common to
yeah that's what's in common to
everything on wholesome yeah
so if something is unwholesome means
there is a
it contains a discrepancy in itself
which is what contradiction is
something that goes against the way
things are
is this and i try to remove that and
replace it with something else
yeah but it's it's not just like go
against the way things are but in itself
is against things are so that
contradiction is in
i'm wholesome it's not between wholesome
and wholesome saying unwholesome things are
wholesome saying unwholesome things are
unwholesome because they go against
wholesome now they are unwholesome because in
now they are unwholesome because in
themselves
they have contradiction
like if i think about the precepts so
you can look at each precept and you can
see that
same thread running through it of
take for killing for example i i'm
taking away that which is not mine
yeah i have no right i have no
in i'm not entitled to your life or to
any other being's life
even to my own life but to take
something which is not mine and
take it away take it as though it were
mine and destroy it yeah
and destroy it yeah
that's yeah so it's a contradiction here
something that's not yours
you're basically destroying as if it
were yours as if you're in charge as a
field in control
this is mine and also also another thing
is
um
life is implicitly valuable for everyone
even by the way people who decide to
who don't necessarily have a view
that the life is worth living still they
can only do that on the basis of being
alive
that's why everybody will fear death
except arahant
it's impossible that you can't be ready
for death even if you want to kill
yourself it will surprise you what death is only
it will surprise you what death is only
other hunt is truly unmoved in the face
of death as the buddha would say
that means that life in itself being
alive is is taken at its face value and it has
is is taken at its face value and it has
that value so
you as the one who implicitly values
life it's taking
life of another that's another
discrepancy of the values pretty much you while you
of the values pretty much you while you
value life
you're now acting to a destroying life
intentionally as their life were not valuable
as their life were not valuable
yeah exactly as though life is not
valuable so that to me it's not like
contradiction between wholesome and
wholesome no it's within yourself within your own
no it's within yourself within your own
values
within your own principles it's actually
that's why unwholesome is universal and
wholesome for everyone
because for everyone it contradicts
those universal values
so it is valuable but then you yeah
you say my life is not valuable you can
only say that on the basis of life with
true value so you're trying to cover it
up you kind of cover up or conceal that
value not explicitly no that's implied in it
not explicitly no that's implied in it
you might not even completely think
about it at all
oh yeah yeah you're not trying to cover
it up yeah
engaging in unwholesome means that's the
discrepancy you're accepting i mean yeah
so all you have to do is not think about
unwholesome all you need to do is not
understand unwholesome
all you need to do is not understand
wholesome you're born up you're born into that
you're born up you're born into that
kind of uh
concealment already pretty much yes
you're not like born with the fully
developed concealments but as the buddha
said all the underlying tendencies for those
all the underlying tendencies for those
concealments are there present
in the newborn so they will grow they
will develop your
that ignorance there it's not something
that you decided to do before no
like you made a choice when you're five
years old i will conceal things now no
no the truth of things uh this is all
mine it's basically ignorance is part of
it's basically ignorance is part of
well pretty much the way you attend to
things it's implicit in it you know when you
it's implicit in it you know when you
attend to something
you automatically have to ignore
something else you cannot attend to
everything so that's that's all that's
the principle of a video by the way
by looking this way you will not be able
to look at the other way at the same
time so which is the most common way that
so which is the most common way that
people choose to look
well it's the way of least resistance
it's the way of centrality
it's the way you feel will it's the way
of passion desire satisfaction
so it's the way basically of the grain
with the flow yeah so automatically
simply attending to that way
means you're not attending to the other
way you cannot attend to the both at the
same time
you have to learn you have to find a
good reason to start looking upstream
and then start swimming upstream while
everything is trying to pull it down
downstream
it just in the precepts again oh and by
the way i just want to say that's why
that's what the only one who truly
understands wholesome is wholesome
and unwholesome as unwholesome as in the
universal value of wholesome and
unwholesome is a sort of honor
so you don't know what's truly skillful
and what's truly unskillful unless you
have the right view
or that whole picture well that's what
the right view is
understanding the universal value of
wholesome and unwholesome and then you
know you will know the root of wholesome and
you will know the root of wholesome and
the root of one wholesome
and when they asked the weather so what
is what is sodom and i said well so one
is the one who knows
uh skillful and skillful or crucial is
kusala also miss wholesome
and he knows an also
so again you would can you say that then
that which is unwholesome is that which
goes against
the way things are
yes but i don't like using the way
things are because that had been
overused and mystified already goes against the
and mystified already goes against the
truth it goes against the universal
principles yeah what are the universal principles
yeah what are the universal principles
that's what the dhamma is the dharma is
the universal law
as the brother would say it goes against
the nature goes against the dhamma
yeah so any that's
so you need to understand the dhamma
universe like be a saudi banner to know what
like be a saudi banner to know what
those universal principles are
which means you can't have an idea
of what the natural natural and nature's
law is
and then define infer from there
what is wholesome you can that can only
be on the level of that kind of abstract
view they can correspond to the practical
they can correspond to the practical
application to some extent some people
can kind of have an accurate
but you haven't truly understood the
nature of wholesome as wholesome
like why is wholesome wholesome do you
see it for yourself
why is unhold some unwholesome do you
see that for yourself
so if we just go to the next that
precept of i think it's
not stealing
not taking something which is not given
to
gain as a whole yeah you're taking away
something which isn't and you can also
that's why like you cannot
accidentally break the precepts
the perception is is is the is the
fundamental factor
if you perceive something is truly yours
and you take it because you perceive it
as yours you mistaken it for something
else looks the same there was yours there's
looks the same there was yours there's
no stealing involved there yeah
stealing requires you your intentional
effort to
override which is what the discrepancy
is
so intentional effort to override the
value of life
which which is implicit even if you
don't think about it intentional effort
to override the value of ownership
which is implicit but you choose to
ignore it intentional effort to go and i
don't know if it's
the five pieces to seduce other people's
partners or cheats again all of the discrepancies
or cheats again all of the discrepancies
that you then intentionally choose to
ignore and double down in your action towards
and double down in your action towards
it that's why
these things are unwholesome
so if you have no perception like like
in the suit as we mentioned it before if
it's like accidentally there was an accident
like accidentally there was an accident
and somebody died as a result of it
um it wasn't it wasn't an offense of
killing like when there's that story in the
like when there's that story in the
winner of the two monks who
got in an argument and then only one of
them had a water filter
yeah and he didn't want to give it to
the other one uh because they were like
i'm not giving
his mind he offended him or something
and then the other monk
died of thirst because he didn't want to
drink it to break the rules so he died
of thirst
as tartan he couldn't recover and then
died and he the first monk wasn't it wasn't
and he the first monk wasn't it wasn't
an offense of killing another monk
because he would have said okay well
next time you should not withhold
anything out of
ill will so he was an offense of of a
completely different kind
not on the level of for he's not a monk
anymore because he killed another monk
no you need to intent so
if that other monk said i will not give
you the water with the intention of
he'll die of thirst yeah then of course
but he had no such intention
so that's why intention is the action
you cannot judge the action the outcome
of actually severe direction
without ignoring the intention behind
or the one we mentioned in the previous
talk the monk we accidentally sat on
that bed like with pillars and there was a
bed like with pillars and there was a
baby underneath and killed
it broke its neck or something and we
said okay well next time if you sit down
without checking where you're sitting
it's an offense of wrongdoing
although the wrongdoing resulted in
death of a baby
but it wasn't intentional
so intention is that factor
if you choose to act with intention of
ill will
desire carelessness means you
you're accepting that contradiction that
value contradicting value
you're choosing to go down that way
because it's too unpleasant to resist it
pretty much
so just let's step back that precept of
um refraining from sexual misconduct or
or
having sexual relations with
uh people you shouldn't you know
another's wife or uh
just taking again misappropriating
things which aren't yeah so you perceive
it you perceive it
generally is not yours as
uh shouldn't be engage with uh
and then you choose to give priority to
your desire and ignore
the factual basis of your perception you
you give priority
to your desires not the others so
mine is first mine is more important
that's why even passion regard even if
it's passion within the precepts
even if it's sort of annoyance and ill
will but you don't break the precepts
that that's what these contradictions
already rooted
when it comes to precepts it's just a
further manifestation
of you acting out of that contradiction
but passion in itself desire in itself
it will in itself
um delusion or or dullness in itself
it's that's in itself that's already that
that's in itself that's already that
contradiction that's why these things
aren't wholesome
and these things always result in
unwholesome so if you if you take the process why is
so if you if you take the process why is
passion
yeah contradiction why is a desire a
contradiction
individually from your own point of view
desire towards anything
why is that desire a con existential
contradiction or contradiction on the
essential level
what is the discrepancy there well you
want something okay
that you cannot have but
i mean you can have things it's not
yours but that doesn't mean you can't have it
but that doesn't mean you can't have it
you just took it
so that's not necessarily contradiction
on a more fundamental level
why is it a contradictory to have a
desire even if you don't go and take it
even if you don't break the precepts why
is it contradictory to have a desire
to cultivate desire to welcome desire to
delight in a desire
so desire is always towards sense
objects you cannot have a desire that's not
you cannot have a desire that's not
towards sense objects
side sounds melted such as thoughts it
always has it's inconceivable
because whatever you desire is going to
be one of these six things
sight sounds smell taste touch thoughts
can you have any of these six things
without the senses being there
without the mind being there can you
have sights without the eye
sounds without ears impossible so what
is the nature
of the eye ear nose body
tongue mind what is the nature of it
yeah so how can you then
cultivate the desire towards that which
you can only get on account of things
that are not yours
the only way you can cultivate desire
towards those things is to take these
things to be yours to begin with
so it's impossible for you to have a
desire to sense objects
without implicitly taking the ownership
of the senses
that's what i i thought i was saying
that actually but
i don't you might have been saying it in
general terms but i didn't kind of see
that you were saying it on the level of
like even if you don't act even if you
don't break the precepts
even if you don't do anything having a
desire that is being welcomed and
delighted in and accepted and not
understood is already that existential
is already that existential
contradiction we talk about because
you will not be able to welcome a desire
entertain it even if you don't act out
of it without that
entertainment of that desire implicitly
taking up
the sense basically jesus as yours yeah
mama taking up mara's domain yeah yeah
that's what i was going to say
just now yes the most the precept of
not um not acting out of sensuality
you know being sure of it sure so you're
no longer taking these senses to be
yours well no not acting out of um
well no not acting out of um
centrality being celibate is the
necessary sort of precondition for you to then
sort of precondition for you to then
eventually not take these senses to be
also on the level of your thought
because that's what would have said a
monk can live withdrawn from centrality
but if he hasn't understood it uprooted
it internally on the level of his
thoughts he's still bound by it
and then gave the simile like you can
step outside of the water
and get the sticks and dry this and get
the sticks to light the fire but because
they're still wet because of their water
you won't light a fire so you need to
wait for them to dry up and not keep
going back to the water so you have to
live withdrawn from centrality
physically as a celibate but then also mentally you
as a celibate but then also mentally you
need to start withdrawing your mind so
it dries up from that centrality
stop taking that which is not yours
exactly because
taking up for what's not yours starts on
the level of welcoming a desire
desire arises by welcoming it you take
it up
when you take up desire you take every
every value
that that desire implies the value is
that senses are in your control
senses can be enjoyed it's not dangerous
to enjoy the senses it's not dangerous
to pursue whatever
it takes are you acting from a premise
that these senses are mine
yeah sense experience is safe secure
all that's implicit yeah lovely yeah all
of that is completely implicit you don't
even you don't know that
the lighting and so on already that's
obviously he doesn't delight so you
can't say desire to desire to not
manifest itself you have no say in that
but you have a saying your attitude
towards the manifestation of desire
or real will for that matter am i
welcoming am i relishing this am i
enjoying am i kind of
rejoicing in the prospect of desire and
then fulfilling that desire
even if then i practice sense restraint
am i still entertaining
a phenomenon of desire in my experience
when desire manifests
and if you do that's why you're still
contradicting yourself on the
existential basis because you cannot
possibly entertain as i said the value of desire
entertain as i said the value of desire
without implicitly taking up the
ownership of the sense basis
so if you stop valuing the sense objects
stop entertaining desire towards them
you get to uproot
taking up the sense basis as as yours
the sense organs as yours you have
desire towards sense objects because you've
towards sense objects because you've
misappropriated
the sense senses yeah it's like a
vicious circle
yeah so because you appropriate the
senses as in you you don't question your
ownership of them
of your eye knows the body that's how
you cultivate desire towards the sense
objects because you cultivate desires to
because you cultivate desires to
essential objects that's how you
appropriate the sense organs
so one feeds the other so first you need
to stop
first you need to start restraining your
behavior on account of the desire to
attend object as in you need to start
keeping the precepts
and then once you're established in that
one that become
once that becomes your norm um norm of
behavior then you can get to see that on the
then you can get to see that on the
mental level
you should now stop delighting in it
welcoming it sort of
flirting it in your mind and accepting
it even if you know you're not gonna act
physically now you make the further effort and
now you make the further effort and
don't welcome it with the mind don't
engage in it
and then eventually through not
basically you you will dry out
of that that wetness of that desire so
to speak
and then you get to see the true nature
of those senses oh my goodness this is
parallel this is like
each time i was engaging with the desire
to sense objects it was like putting my
head on a chopping block which is what the
on a chopping block which is what the
sense organ is
and the acts could have fallen at any
given time balancing on this
this this
unsecured thing well yeah you're
basically because of your desire to
attend to organs the trees
you go into a trap yeah sorry because
your desire to sense objects you go into
the trap
of central organs
and that's without we done that that the
simulator the lions reserve
so you you are making yourself like
you're exposing yourself to this danger
to this peril to this risk to death
deadly suffering because of your desire
to sense objects which implies the
ownership of sense organs
and since organs are that chopping block
are that are that k
are that uh trap and lions then and so
on that you walk into them
but you can't just say okay i'm not
regarding my senses is mine anymore
because that thought of your senses it's
basically a sense object
right so you cannot directly experience
your sense organs which is why
all that implicit ownership that you
need to undo indirectly
you can't just decide i'll let go of
this because you're not holding it
intentionally so there is what else do you need to let
so there is what else do you need to let
go or rather what is the only other
thing that you
if you let go then you will not have the
ownership of the sense organs
all right it's a to send objects let go
of that
you step closer to then let go of the
sense organs
but if you think you're letting go of
sense organs you're regarding your own
sense of organs as sense objects
so not being uh
overly in into the perceptions
what do you mean by that well you're not
delighting it you're not focusing and
you're not
entangled within your perceptions you
can let go of them so to speak
to step back to see what's behind it
what they are
based upon yeah
but like when you see when you want to
see what's behind it's not like another
thing you want to see
just you mustn't act out of it out of
that delight and desire
and then you need to understand it
understand that desire there's nothing
else you need to sort of
psychologize out of it to figure it out
you just need to understand
the nature of that thing which is right
there that desire
the peril the danger that's why i keep
saying it's implicit
it's not found in response to this
desire or after it's in it
all of that is in every desire in every
time you delight in any desire of any
kind all these things are implicit
all these universal values are implicit
so that's what i mean like the eye
cannot see itself
literally so the sense organs cannot see
itself as a sense object
or or of its corresponding nature it's
impossible utterly impossible so when you think
utterly impossible so when you think
you're letting go of your eyes of your
body you're not you're basically that that
you're not you're basically that that
thought is misconceiving sense objects
to be the sense organ because yes you
can imagine an eye
but that's not the eye because of which
you have sights
so the only way to abandon the eye
because of which to abandon the
ownership of i
because of which you have sights is to
see the peril of the desire towards
science the danger
to no delight in it when you have
sufficiently seen that the mind will
withdraw itself from the domain of sight
and by doing so implicitly we draw that
ownership of the domain of sites as
i the sense object of the site
that's why it's a trap you you are
alert by something else driven by
something else and you walk into a trap
you never see the trap
otherwise he wouldn't trap you
yes so you withdraw yourself from the
particular bait that traps you and
that's how you escape the trap
and you can't see the trap but you can
see the bait and what is the bait
desire in regard to sights is the mars
bait yeah so you remove the desire to what
yeah so you remove the desire to what
sides
you see there is no entering the trap of
any kind so you don't need to worry
about the
like specificity of a trap
this is how it works when i think this
they said no no desire towards sights
no trap of any kind that you can walk
into
i think what's it the next precept
after we did we did the third we did
yeah well it's the lying isn't it i said
well it's the lying isn't it i said
lying already no no
it was stealing yeah
misrepresenting the truth exactly
intentionally yeah but fundamentally
you are you are living concealment
exactly yeah
that is the biggest lie which you kind
of yeah
yeah the biggest lie is is that the
fundamental lie of
uh uh ignorance then
i don't want to use oregon that's
necessarily of a video the fundamental
eye of
delusion dullness
like would you be able for example
to be complacent lazy
dull and careless if you're placed in a
dangerous situation
did you perceive the danger of it it
would be inconceivable for you
to relax on that level to like
completely just
let your mind kind of melt away and
forget about itself
and yet here you are in the most
perilous situation you can be
with death sickness aging everything
else is approaching
elements from all the directions you
can't escape it and yet here you are
completely complacent it's like the
fundamental contradiction the hardest
one to undo
because it's not as obvious as desire or
as you will there is danger but you just
don't see it
but it's implied you feel it that's the
thing it's not like the danger doesn't
exist just for example if you if you want to
just for example if you if you want to
do a little experiment if you're not
sure if it's dangerous
or not your existence in itself just
lock yourself in the room
comfortable room but don't engage with
any distraction for a day
switch your phone off switch everything
don't talk to anyone don't step outside
just sit alone in a chair or a bed
whatever else and stare in the wall
and let's see how long you can do that
before you start freaking out on account
of that
boredom so if boredom is not truly
dangerous why are you so afraid of it why do you
why are you so afraid of it why do you
constantly need something to keep you
engaged to swim
so you don't sink deep down why are you
terrified of solitude and loneliness
which like 99.99 people are because you
need to make the effort
to basically develop your mind and
wisdom in order to delight
in solitude so you then
you realize that oh if i'm safe i get
sick and i can't move
so i can't distract myself with all
these things and projects i have to do
how will my mind remain will it be
unaffected by this
or will i start completely losing it and
freaking out so that's why like boredom
out so that's why like boredom
so i'm bored yeah let the boredom endure
now and it's going to turn into
full-blown anxiety and dread and why is that if
anxiety and dread and why is that if
existence is not
dangerous and perilous where does this
anxiety come from because you haven't
done anything by the way
you're in a perfectly safe environment
locked nobody can get in
safe as you can be and yet here you are
freaking out internally
well because that's what existence is
it's all these efforts and actions you
do
to enable yourself to ignore that very
nature so that's what delusion like globa
so that's what delusion like globa
the three kind of unwholesome outposts
that's why they're unwholesome
the illusion being the third one or
download that dullness
is a form of complacency and the only
way you like you cannot be complacent
without implicit
kind of uh without implicitly sort of
assuming or ignoring the fact that it's not
or ignoring the fact that it's not
dangerous
that existence is not perilous so you
just assume safety
because you are complacent and in com
because you assume safety
you you make the effort with complacency
same like with that
what we said with the desire and but i
think one has to understand that what a
nietzsche
by seeing a nietzsche and by seeing a
nietzsche's dukkha you then implicitly
withdrawing yourself from the ownership
of atta
which is anata but that scene means that
you are no longer yeah
complacent yeah so you need to see that
dukkha and the duke of of boredom
is the duke of this is the duke of
uneasiness it says there's so many reds
this is
seeing that duke is like seeing uh your
executioner with his
sword drawn out waiting for you wait
it's there he's waiting for you so you
have that
you can't go you can't relax and yeah
just watch a movie now well
yeah yeah exactly well like somebody
comes and tells you you have ten minutes
to live
okay thank you i'll just carry on
watching this movie and laughing
carelessly it would be impossible for you to do
it would be impossible for you to do
that because suddenly the sense of
urgency is back on
you the only reason signs of urgency can
be kind of restored is because it's
always there implicit
anxiety that threat of anxiety that you
can never completely cover up
is what human existence is for everyone
people who break these people who don't
practice nobody can outrun it
only arahant can free himself from it
completely so yeah
by trapping yourself into a room or
whatever yeah so but when you're like
young healthy you have all the senses
working everything at your disposal
it feels like there's no problem as i
said just do a little experiment
close yourself in for like half a day
and see what babies
see what's going to start happening to
your own mind when there are no
distractions available
and if your mind was problem free
beforehand this would not cause any
issues yet
it does so it should start you're
revealing what's actually there
exactly taking away well you're
revealing what what what
what's your main motivator for all this
engagement with life
is to cover up the fact that it's
perilous and underlying anxiety that
sort of means you're not in control so
that as you said before that
the whole practice is about unconcealing
things or in the suit as it says yeah
i'm doing moving this and conceiving
which is covered like there's
like a skill butcher gets the first you
know the skin off to me the sa
the tendons sinews everything uncovering
not like analyzing on an abstract level
which is sometimes how people take it no
no
means uncovering all the layers of a
cover up
until you get to the core
just and fifth precepts
on intoxicants yeah that's exactly it
can you possibly engage with
intoxicating substances
without implicitly endorsing complacency
and dullness of your mind
inconceivable inconceivable just have
fun inconceivable oh it's just like you know
inconceivable oh it's just like you know
i don't necessarily get drunk doesn't
matter engaging with that substance to some
engaging with that substance to some
extent
is increasing dullness of your mind it's
impossible or the heatlessness unless there is no
or the heatlessness unless there is no
alcohol in the substance
which always results in increasing well
dullness means heatlessness tarnish
means loss of context loss of perspective even
loss of context loss of perspective even
if it's for a grain a bit
like not as much as you're completely
drunk it's still
the direction of losing context and
perspective even if it's half a step
it's still that same thing so as they
would have said same
a pound of excrement is equally
disgusting as a little grain of it
smells horrible looks horrible and
tastes horrible
so the fact that you engage little bit
maybe oh i only take a glass of wine i
don't get drunk
doesn't matter oh i only take a scoop of
excrement it's still the result of dullness even
it's still the result of dullness even
if it's minuscule
mental dullness is still the result of
your action which means you still value
it
you're still engaging with it you can
you engage with even even even like a
sort of absolute minimal um
level so to speak of uh
intoxication just tiny bit without
valuing without without delighting at the
without without delighting at the
prospect of of dullness of the mind
preferring that yeah numbness dullness
distraction any of it
so which means can you can you be
engaging with that direction
of intoxicating your mind even tiny bit
without sort of
uh not seeing the danger of it would you
be able to engage with it if you see it
as dangerous
well i will not go all the way into the
lion's den i'll just set the foot inside
yeah but what if the lion is right there
by the entrance because there is a
chance that it might be
then you wouldn't do it you wouldn't
flirt with that idea at all
a little bit of poison exactly a little
bit of poison is still a poison
it doesn't affect you it's a lot of
poison but it's still a poison which
means it still affects you
which means that might be enough in
itself
because you're already covered like
you're already full of wrong views in
regard to everything in regard to
desire in regards to ill will in regard
to dullness so it's already
like a mountain of work for all of that
to be undone as we said
and yet here you are flirting with the
things that directly result in
increasing of those wrong views
so yes literally a glass of wine
might be enough for you to fully cement
you know wrong views that sensuality is
not bad or not
not see it as dangerous enough and
because of that you will not get the
right view and you will remain bound to
samsara for runes to come is the glass of wine
for runes to come is the glass of wine
really worth that risk
do you really know that that risk is not
implied not the slightest clue
you just wishful thinking and believe in
it because
yes you perceive that it's not as bad as
as two liters of wine
but it doesn't mean it's not bad
it's based on the same thing it's it's
the same thing yeah
there's a whole it had taken intoxicants
so fifth piece of identity and that's
what they were sorry there was that case
of a man with the right view in the
sutta who was drinking
who wasn't practicing he got a right
view then stopped practicing
because he was happy with the with the
right view and then got careless in his
presets
but then when he was basically dying he
undertook the training again
and pretty much stopped drinking even if
it's like for a day it doesn't matter
he had the basis of right view so the
buddha said well for him
it was different because why doesn't
matter even if he was absolutely pissing
drunk every single day of his life having
every single day of his life having
developed the right view beforehand
he cannot develop the wrong views now
he's certainly not pursuing the
direction of the right view that results
in our handship
but he cannot undo the right view right
so the amount of drinking the amount of
engaging in breaking the precepts cannot
proliferate his wrong views
which is exactly what happens to
somebody without the right view
and it's also exactly why it's very
unlikely that somebody with the right
view would break those precepts like
that i mean yeah there is always exception to
i mean yeah there is always exception to
every rule and that's why two and a half
thousand years later we're still
talking about that man that's when he
made it into the suitors he stood out
most of them would not do that so for
whatever reasons he had his reasons
one in a million has done that but now
you use that one example
pretty much anecdotal evidence to say
that you without the right view is fine
to drink because sodapana can drink
okay so drinking you can match that why
don't you match the right view of a soda
pan as well and then see how you can
drink or how you can break the precepts sure
or how you can break the precepts sure
theoretically you could
but not until you get the right view
first so i'm just explaining like how it did
so i'm just explaining like how it did
not affect him
i mean it affected him obviously because
he could have become another hunt in
this life
but it did not affect him in the same
sense if somebody without a right view
even just not seeing the danger in the
tiny little step
towards intoxication and dullness might
be more than enough for fully
solidifying wrong views that you should
have been undoing
which means you will not you will not
get the right view as a result of you
lacking development on the on in the domain of
development on the on in the domain of
precepts
and even like we posted that before
the suitors were never even when was
teaching lay people before they would
get the right view
he would start teaching them the like
you know
benefits of virtue uh generosity and
then the peril of centrality
heights out of little value little
satisfaction and then when the mind will be primed
and then when the mind will be primed
like that then he would teach it and
then they would get understand and then
they might go back to their wives and
husbands and so on
but they cannot do what they understood
which means they'll never be able to be
as careless
so yeah if you get the right view and
then choose to go back to sensuality
that's your choice but saying because
the one with the right view can go to
centrality means i can do centrality
without a right view
well that's just ignorant thinking
intentional ignorant thinking
because you obviously see that it's not
the same
well it's it's similar to intoxication
intoxication with life intestination
with health it talks occasionally
yes yeah of course of course that's what
i mean losing the context
yeah that's the context is that oh yeah
i might be healthy and alive and young
now but
do can i guarantee that that would be
the next in and out breath i'll be like
no
you have absolutely no guarantee of that
but when you don't think about that
that's so when you fall away from recognizing
so when you fall away from recognizing
that context then you start heading into
the direction of the
desire towards sense objects which is
intoxication as well so that's the more
subtle application of that precept yeah yeah
application of that precept yeah yeah
sure sure you can go deeper there yeah
taking no intoxicants yeah no longer
intoxicated oh but i don't get drunk when i drink
oh but i don't get drunk when i drink
one one glass of wine or one beer but
you're intoxicated with life
being drunk is not a measure of whether
you're wholesome and wholesome
engaging with the unwholesome direction
is a measure
so doesn't matter if you engage 10 steps
into the unholstered direction of one
step you're accepting the direction of
you're accepting the direction of
unwholesome full stop
but it's this again like a common sort
of protruding as wisdom well i don't get
drunk nobody says you shouldn't get
drunk you shouldn't drink alcohol but not
you shouldn't drink alcohol but not
drinking alcohol you cannot get drunk
but is this the drunk is being the
problem no drinking alcohol is a problem
not because you get drunk but because
it's implicitly
taking up of the unwholesome direction
even a tiny bit
and then you won't have to be worried
about whether you're drunk or not
that was never the the threshold for the
preset
there was never a distraction yeah the
priest doesn't say don't get drunk it
says don't consume intoxicants
they then result in drugs and so on but
i don't get drunk no it doesn't matter
have you consumed intoxicants yes would
you be able to consume intoxicants
without implicit value of mental dullness and
implicit value of mental dullness and
relaxation
basically on the level of ignoring the
the necessary context of perilous
existence hey you're gonna die in five minutes but
hey you're gonna die in five minutes but
let's have a glass of wine let's forget
about it
let's get drunk help you deal with it no
is there anything i can do
like i might have a chance to save
myself yeah you have a chance to save
yourself but
forget about it let's drink let's enjoy
ourselves which one would you choose even as the
which one would you choose even as the
one who
values alcohol and party and everything
else you would choose to do something
about it
when you recognize that you could so the
only reason now you will be accepting
the direction of distraction
intoxication relaxation
on the level of mental dullness would be
because you're completely unaware of the danger
you're completely unaware of the danger
and you will not become aware of the
danger on account of choosing the
direction of unwholesome
and that's the other precepts of
uh yeah no entertainment no uh
decoration oh we're now going to eight presents
oh we're now going to eight presents
yeah i mean in general you can you can
right right right in any piece well same same
right right in any piece well same same
can you
engage with entertainment um
beautification and adornment without
and adornment without
implying the ownership of that which
you're entertaining adoring
and beautifying without implying the
value of this thing is beautiful and worth
of this thing is beautiful and worth
embellishment
like would you be embellishing a
poisonous drink
that just smelling it might kill you let
alone touching it or drinking it
you wouldn't go near it why would you
then sort of
spend your time like dressing it up
and why do you need to dress it up in
the first place i mean
if it's already beautiful and wonderful
would you dress up a pile of excrement
no amount of dress will make a pile of
excrement uh
attractive you just wouldn't so you will
only dress up something that you can
perceive that can be
embellished even more by dressing up
by adorning by beautifying by covering
up the ugly so i can emphasize the
beautiful means you imply it's beautiful
and that's already a contradiction in
terms because it isn't beautiful if it's
beautiful it would be in your control
you wouldn't age you wouldn't be
subjected to elements you wouldn't be
subjected to dying sickness
you wouldn't be subjected to basically
uh everything else that's going on in
the body that you conveniently ignored
every single time you choose to only
single out one aspect that's
not as ugly that's what we spoke before
people think things are beautiful and
then ugly then they can say oh this is
beautiful and less beautiful but
actually if you practice correctly
sense restraint and develop wisdom it's
going to be ugly and even more ugly
there's nothing beautiful anymore
because there is no beauty in danger and
peril and deadly suffering and trap even if
and deadly suffering and trap even if
it's a perfectly engineered beautifully
dressed trap
it's still a perilous trap and you are a
subject of it so you will be scared
you will not be beautifying it you will
be highlighting its danger its ugliness
so the only way you would engage in any
form of even that tiny bit of
beautification is by not seeing the
danger in the angle and saw it by
ignoring it
by choosing to not attend to it excuse
me against the cover
it's a cover-up again another
discrepancy yeah and
so in terms of karma
action
so this is the result of action
the result of your actions is
reality reasserting itself
which reality what are you talking about
what do you mean reality
by reality i mean the nature of things
pushing back to in terms of that uh
consumer that you are engaged with
right right well that's on nature things
but what reasserts itself
is already that attitude of ignoring and
covering up
that's the proliferation so the more you
engage the more of the unwholesome karma you do
the more of the unwholesome karma you do
the result the direct result here and
now will be reinforcing of the
underlying ignoring of those values which is what
ignoring of those values which is what
your value is it's basically
underlying wrong views underlying uh
lack of context of danger
peril and so on that's what you're
enforcing that's what grows it
reinforces because
it's going against that's which
that which is yeah but that doesn't mean
that which is it's it's it's brought up
more it's simply covered up even more
well exactly
that's why karma keeps you bound to the
trap yeah not that
the the truth will reveal itself by the
more you
can't try to conceal it it's the more
that you try conceal it
the more you will try to conceal it
because yeah the more bound to concealment of
yeah the more bound to concealment of
the truth you become
the more dependent on it it sort of
emphasizes
what the truth that you
so you know you wouldn't you wouldn't
use the word truth it's not the truth
you don't see it's not it's a lie for
you the emphasis
is your life in order to lie there has
to be an implicit truth
yeah yeah which you don't but it's not
emphasized what is emphasized is the lie
that's your starting point has no
relationship with the truth
the moment he gets it he becomes a soda
punch yeah
he knows the truth i know but that's why
it's not correct to say or reinforces or
emphasizes the truth for whom
for saudi banana that's not the case
because he got the truth for putin our
old thing that's emphasized is a lie
so the statement is abstractly true what
you say
but practically unapplicable which is
why i
that's why i'm saying it's not correct i
know what you're describing in theory
and yes but that theory if it's not
applicable to either type of individual
it's not a right theory
but yes in order to maintain a lie you
kind of carry the truth with you but
that doesn't mean you're a step closer
to understanding it
so if i do something good i give there
is a result
that emphasizes
that which i've just done yeah
is that that's i mean i don't i mean i
might feel joy i'm not specific
i might feel joy i might you might say
thank you
because that act that i've done is good
it's there's a good result it's kind of
this by the way why is generosity good
why is it wholesome why is generosity
free from discrepancy
it's still an action it's still a comma
but in itself why is generosity good
there's no there's no concealment there
there's no
cover-up there's no taking away which is
not no i'm still very conceited and arrogant
no i'm still very conceited and arrogant
and i gave it to you for selfish reasons
but the act of giving is still good my
reasons are really selfish
i don't even like you but yet that act
of giving is still good
well that because that's degree of is
nothing's been concealed there
in that whole act i'm doing it for
myself yes i'm doing it for you yes i'm not
yes i'm doing it for you yes i'm not
pretending that
well doing things for yourself is
concealment through your own conceit
which already misperceives yeah i mean
no no i'm just talking about the action
of giving like the action of taking from
you is bad in itself
the action of giving is good in itself
why is action of giving
good in itself well yeah i mean before
you're saying that
because it uh emulates that right order
of things
right right well yeah pretty much pretty
much now i would say differently in a
sense that
like giving or taking away
as we well as we described in relation
to taking things away
fundamentally you are in no position to
exercise any ownership
even on account of your own sense or the
organs left on everything else you can
experience through it
so giving up means relinquishing of
ownership however symbolic by the way
you don't even need to think about it
giving something it mirrors
the non-ownership that's why it's good
mirrors the impossibility to own right
right mirrors the the possibility of
mirrors the the possibility of
relinquishing the ownership even if you
don't make the effort and that's what i
mean good karma will not free you from karma
good karma will not free you from karma
you can give all you want
but underneath all of that you still
value the ownership you still imply the
ownership of your sense of self your
body and everything else
but because it it uh emulates that
it emulates that which you don't see not
understand right that's why
that's why that's what is good and
that's why it will make you like as
would you say you'll be even in better
realms right the basically that the reserve for
right the basically that the reserve for
those who have not been so dependent
in this life on desire aversion and
distraction so it's more in line with
the truth
or it's more in line with the nature of
things okay you can see it's more in
line with the universal principles
so now if i act uh opposed to those
universal principles
i do something unwholesome uh i don't
know how to say it
is uh the result of that
the result of that yeah the
well the result of that emphasizes that
something is not right that for whom
for a third person observer for me no
no you won't see that that's what more
centrality will bring more sensuality
more sexuality cannot emphasize the
problem of sensuality
only you turning away from sensuality
like with your own reflection upon the
centrality engaged
that's what i mean you you're thinking
about it accurately but abstractly
so if i'm looking at so if i'm if i'm
looking at it another person
i'm looking at you acting badly yeah and
then i see you get bad results
and then i can say i know why you're
getting bad results
because you're not in a living in
accordance with
the dumber you're going against the
nature of things that's why
yeah but that but that means you have
you understand the law of karma
and how i got the bad results on account
of this or that
but can't you can't you understand the
law of karma
on that basis no you can understand the
wholesomeness wholesaling holsters is
unwholesome so you can know whatever
goes through the gateway of
contradicting that
maintaining that existential
contradiction will be unwholesome
whatever goes through the gateway
and will result in unwholesome yeah yeah
of course sure
but to what extent you don't know that
no yeah i'm not saying no you don't
that's exactly yeah desire
aversion and distraction will always
result in unwholesome
they cannot as it would have said
wholesome action cannot result in
unwhole can cannot have unwholesome
results a wholesome action cannot have wholesome
a wholesome action cannot have wholesome
results impossible
so what are you trying to say still
so the universal law the natures law the
principles we're talking about it
they're either abstractly true or true
in case of an argument
so yeah so what i was i was saying was
that the results of
action is
the universal principle
asserting itself that's how it started
yeah yeah
reasserting yes the right order
yeah no that's not right why isn't it
right let's explain it
because there is no right order it's the
wrong order
unless you are so upon or higher so the
only thing you're reasserting is the
wrong order of the universal principle
but because there are results of actions
yeah because if there was the right
order would there be results of
your actions yeah your actions
yeah because now you're talking about
the order of actual physical action
but except for in our hands he's gone
beyond camera
yeah well he is uprooted to come
he hasn't gone beyond it for as long as
he's alive in other words
things that he's to experience on the
level of body and and
and elements he will still experience in
this life but there will be
any future lives for him to experience
that
you're obscuring the fact that you can
do good and still not be free from karma
you can do bad you can do good both are
doing are not rooted in the action they are
are not rooted in the action they are
rooted in whether you
see the universal principle or you don't
see the universal principle
so sort of in higher sees the universal
principle which is why he has a limited
amount of rebirth
and eventually he's completely impari
nibana not seeing the universal principle means
not seeing the universal principle means
you're still going to be equally born
just in better places maybe if you were
doing good
so acting out of non-seeing of universal
principle reassert the not seeing of universal
reassert the not seeing of universal
principle
so you need to stop acting out of not
seeing the universal principle as in
you need to stop doing unwholesome
things you need to start being virtuous
and keeping the precepts
and then you might get to see the
universal principle because at least
you're not contradicting it anymore
on all layers of action but it's not
guaranteed you'll still see it
you can be virtuous for the rest of your
life and still remain a put together
so the only thing that matters but if
you whether universal principle
makes a difference or not is whether
it's seen or not not whether you act
with it accordingly or not
you can act with it accordingly and
still not understand i mean yeah
well that's what i'm saying that's why
it's wrong what you said not seeing the
seeing or not seeing the universal
principle is what matters yeah right
so the only time the universal principle
will be reasserted
is for the one who saw that which can be
now reasserted oh yeah okay okay
but if so you don't see the universe
it doesn't mean that it's not there no
it's possibility of seeing it is there but
possibility of seeing it is there but
the universal principle is the universe
a principle you don't see it otherwise
it wouldn't be universal
even if you don't see it doesn't mean
that it's not it's not the case
so i don't what universe principle there
is no universal principles i don't see
it
and that's why you're basically uh
perverting it that's why you're bound by
it
wrongly yeah but that's why then
i would be affected by
actions yeah
that's correct but that's not correct to
say that that's why you would be
reaffirming the universal principle
no no no yeah i don't mean to actually
imply that i don't mean to apply that i
know i know
but that's how you were phrasing it
right like you reasser the universal
principle by acting out of it
no
yeah acting i cannot reassert the
universal principle
i don't mean because acting out is
already within the universe principle
so that universal principle that your
action cannot step outside
or reaffirm or deny your action is the
universal principle
can either be seen which will then free
you from action or not seen which keeps
you bound with the action
and the direction that that action takes
keeps you powerful yeah
so i think if you want to understand why
your statement was wrong to begin with
stop implying that your action is kind
of in response to universal principle
action is fully enclosed within the
universe cannot step outside of it
yeah yeah in a way good action bad
action neutral action
within the universal principle so you
wouldn't say that that which is already
within universal principle
is reaffirming the universal principle
by acting that's impossible
reaffirmation of your action is again
within the same universal principle
whether that principle is understood or
not that's what they shared
that's why sotheban is one who knows
good karma
as good karma and bad karma as bad now
he doesn't know the results of it
he knows the nature of it so he
understands that this section is
within the right direction of the
universal principle
and then he understands that this
direction is within the wrong sorry this
action is within the wrong direction
within the universal principle which is
why it's wrong but the protruding
acts but doesn't know the universal
principle which
is that's why he's not free from karma
yeah he doesn't know that he's acting
he doesn't know he can take uh on faith
on trust on authority the reasons for
acting good
but that doesn't mean he understood the
nature of action so he but he's affected
by his actions
yeah his actions will take him in the
direction that basically you choose them
to
but if he knows the universal principle
then that
how far you'll go in that direction will
be limited yeah
he won't be affected or not at most in
this life
if he's an arahant and then he'll yeah
he will not be affected
like when when he went to pentapod later
on he became another hunt
and some people recognized him and
they're throwing stones and sticks at
him and beating him and he came back
blooded bruised like in pain and the buddha said
bruised like in pain and the buddha said
ah buried brahman bear it
you are bearing out results of your
actions now
which you would have done otherwise for
eons to come
but this is it this is all you're gonna
have left over from the horrible things
you've done is these
few stones so they are those are the
results of his previous actions although
he's in our hand
you realize these results are on the
level of elements
other people everything else basically
that can be fold this body this
this five aggregates but he has a limit
because he's out by being an argument
like when this breaks apart these aggregates
when this breaks apart these aggregates
there will be not new ones being taken
up
so then the amount of that direction
that can be suffered endured
or enjoyed on account of your good
previous actions is sort of cut off
finished for so dependent it was a seven
lifetimes anagami once returned that's
why it was a measure
of your progress indeed how far you can
sort of carry on
as a result of previous actions but
that's it
because what for the soldier for
whatever whatever he does
he will be within that span of it so at
most yes
so whatever he does let me try again
that same thing whatever he does
reasserts the universal principle in a way reminds
the universal principle in a way reminds
him of that universal question yeah
because he has understood it so whatever
so you can't say the only only that's
what i mean like
if you speak in a third person sense
you can say universal principle is there
that's what i say element of nibana is
present you can everybody can theoretically
you can everybody can theoretically
develop nibana
but it doesn't mean that the one like
from the point of view of a person
if you're not seeing it you're not
having it yeah
but it sounds upon us seeing it he has
it and then yes
everything would be reaffirming even if
he doesn't wholesome
he will be reminded of the wholesome
underlying can't go that far
that's why he can't go that far in
unwholesome he can't go that far in all
the actions you can do on a kind of
breaking the precepts and that's why he
can't go that far
on account of the rebuilds they will
wait for you on account of those bad
actions you congregate fine
yeah so like we can say the statement
you said everything you do reaffirms
or reassert universal principle is true
for sotapanna ohio
not for the one below because if you
allow petunia to partake in that
statement that would equal like when
people read
oh the element of the ban is present in
everyone's experience
and the people are we are already in
ibana as you have the mahayana schools
saying the buddha nature and ibana is always
the buddha nature and ibana is always
there you don't need to do anything
like greed aversion delusion a symptom
of non-buddha nature and non-nibana
freedom from greed divergent delusion
means yes you can get your buddha nature
and your nirvana
but you can't have it both so which one
is it
but if people develop a view that this
abstract possibility of nibana is what nibana is
possibility of nibana is what nibana is
they will not get free from the symptoms
that prevent him to get nibana here and
now and even the buddha talked about it like
and even the buddha talked about it like
when a man not free from greed the
virgin delusion
says oh i i'm absolutely born i am in
the ban i'm attaining the ban he says
yeah sometimes
if he made the effort he'll be factually
stating that which ibana is
but he wouldn't be attaining it because
he's not free from his own conceit and
self of you
i am so that's not the nibana
so that's not the universal principle
because you're not seeing it
it's just abstractly not applicable to
your experience that
contradicts it through greed aversion
and dullness and distraction
so theoretically you are within the
universal principle
either but you're going against it by
not being free from greed aversion
delusion means your values are against the
means your values are against the
universal principle
so the more you act out of the values
that are against it the more you're
reinforcing the
againstness of values not that which
you're against
so just to
end or recap saying what is common to
everything that's unwholesome is that
that view of or that act of
misappropriating things taking that which is not yours
things taking that which is not yours
concealing that which
is yeah and what's in common by the way
to
misappropriating concealing taking up
the attitude what's the the common
thread one
that's it that's that's the root of all
things all things are rooted in conceiving
see the fact that you're conceiving
already means misconceiving
already means putting yourself first
that second taking the only implying the
ownership lack of cut
all of that comes from simple conceiving
i am in this i am from this this is for
me
and so on this is for me therefore i am
yeah all that all that
and so that's so i i i was trying to
come up with a term for that
a petuna in that sense one who conceives
he's a thief what is he
sure however like that wouldn't be
it's kind of more like a it would be an
impassioned statement he's a thief
but it's not accurate because in order
to be a thief you need to perceive the
lack of ownership
doesn't perceive that so he's a victim
of his own ignorance
that results in being acting like a
thief and so on
that's why that's not that that
conceiving and ignoring these things
it's not to deliver lying of
like lying to yourself because in order
to lie to yourself you know the truth
you're just trying to cover it up
he's just ignoring and choosing to
always emphasize a certain direction of
least resistance
of pleasure avoidance of pain all the
values that
a minor petrogena would be acting out of
sensuality ill will
and delusion but you can now equally
choose to not act to which will then
start to reveal that which you have been
ignoring
that's what i mean your attention is
already implying ignorance
but you don't want to ignore the context
you want to ignore sensuality
by all means by the way engage in a
video towards centrality
towards ill will and towards delusion
and distraction
break the precepts kill avija kill the
passion kill ill will kill the
distraction get rid of it do away with it
get rid of it do away with it
and that's what i said yeah no there are
things you should kill
right there so you you just keep
choosing to ignore
other things because you keep choosing
to follow pleasure and avoid pain
at face value but if you start making
the effort on account of buddhist
instruction no don't attend to this don't attend to
no don't attend to this don't attend to
that ignore
possibility of sensuality that's all you
need to do by the way
in the same sense you ignore everything
else when you choose to go down the path
of sensuality
just ignore centrality and go everywhere
else
when there is essential desire ignore it
don't welcome it don't entertain it
don't engage with it don't feed it just
ignore that
let it die away
reassert the universe principle so by
ignoring the desire now you are
automatically have to look the other way the way
have to look the other way the way
you've been ignored by by giving into
the desire
that's why attention is not as well that
is not a single thing in the world
they will bring sensuality to increase
and non-centrality to decrease
as improper attention as wrong intention
and there is not a single thing in the
world that will bring centrality to
decrease and non-centrality decrease as proper
and non-centrality decrease as proper
attention
so when there is a prospect of central
desire present itself
take it if you can take it at a face
value and start attending to its
beautiful aspects that would be
entertaining even more
automatically implicitly you're ignoring
the context of parallel
of it danger lack of satisfaction
um poison basically the threat to the
trap everything is beautiful
non-beautiful so now you can choose to make the effort
so now you can choose to make the effort
to restrain yourself from going down the
path of centrality offered
and then start to reflect on the greater
picture and then automatically you cannot be
and then automatically you cannot be
aware of the greater picture of
centrality which is oh this is not
really that satisfactory
and at the same time be equally
attracted to it impossible it's mutually
exclusive so if you start making effort in the
so if you start making effort in the
direction of greater picture you will be
less and less
pulled by the centrality
so your attention determines the
direction where your mind will be
proliferating too
going so the more you attend to
sexuality the more you're leaning
towards it the more you will attend to
it the more you lean towards
that's why some people are more
dependent on central distractions some
people less
yeah but if you have that bigger picture
there's you have to start cultivating the bigger
you have to start cultivating the bigger
picture by not taking the little picture
at face value and just jumping down
yeah so sensory strain needs to come
first the virtue needs to come first
and then you get to oh there is a bigger
picture but if now i start making more effort on
but if now i start making more effort on
account of the bigger picture towards
the bigger picture and attend that
at the expense of attending to the
particular picture
within it you'll start withdrawing from
centrality right
no matter how far you've proliferated no
matter how far proliferated
the way is always up it can go out of it
doesn't matter how far your preferences
went before
because that thing can yeah it's uh
dispassion towards that when you see
this yeah it's a dispassion to its whole
domain exactly so as you said i've got a dead
exactly so as you said i've got a dead
tree
right around like a palm stomped up at
the root he killed the roots all these
branches of
they proliferated in the past while they
were feeding it they stayed but now it's
gone the life of it is gone so that's that
the life of it is gone so that's that
was
that's the whole point you don't need to
be now cutting the branches down because
they're dead they're not gonna grow
they cannot induce more centralized it's
all finished
that's why another hand would still
remember things he used to enjoy
yeah oh i used to like this it's not
like that i used to have
wives do like whatever the thing with
the music at night and so on
now i have no desire towards that
anymore but i still remember what i used
to enjoy
while i was imminent